《龙猫》
爸爸，牛奶糖
(GASPS)
谢谢
你们两个累不累啊
- Hey Dad, want some caramel?    - Thanks. How you doing back there?
就快到了
- Fine.    - Are you tired? Oop!
- Mmm-mmm.    - We're almost there.
小美，快躲起来
还以为是警察呢！
Mei, hide.
Whoops. I thought that was a policeman.
Hi!
(BOTH LAUGHING)
有没有人在家啊？
谢谢
Hello there. Are your parents around? We're your new neighbors.
我姓草壁　新搬来的
Great. Thanks.
请多关照
Hello! Hi, we're the Kusakabes! We're moving in down the street.
搬家辛苦了
Why don't you and your family stop by sometime?
MAN: Okay, sure. Good to meet you.
谢谢你
Uh!
Hey, thanks a lot.
好，到了
(WATER RUNNING)
等等我吧
This is it, girls.
(GRUNTING)
小美，有座桥啊
- Wait up!    - Here you go.
有桥？
Mei, look at this bridge.
有鱼呢，又闪了一下
A bridge?
怎么样？喜不喜欢？
There's a fish! Oh, look! There's another one!
爸爸，这里好棒啊
So, how do you like the new place?
树林中还有隧道啊
Dad, it's perfect.
那就是新家吗？
Look at this. A tunnel of trees.
Oh, wow! Look!
跑快一点！
(GIGGLING)
Dad, hurry!
很旧啊
好像一间鬼屋
Wow! It's creepy.
鬼屋
Creepy!
- It looks like it could be haunted.    - What, haunted?
(CREAKING)
Whoa.
柱子烂掉了
(GRUNTS) Whoa.
Look. It's rotten.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
(GRUNTING)
要倒了！
(SCREAMS)
(LAUGHING)
- It's collapsing!    - It's collapsing!
(BOTH LAUGHING)
(WHOOPING)
小美，妳看
(BOTH LAUGHING)
(GASPS)
妳看
- Mei, look at that.    - Huh?
Look.
好大啊
- Wow! It's huge, isn't it?    - Ah-choo!
爸爸，好大的树啊
(LAUGHING)
(DOORS SLIDING)
那叫做樟树
Dad, what's that big tree?
樟树呢
Uh, that's a camphor tree.
樟树
- A camphor tree.    - Camphor tree!
Don't forget to take your shoes off, girls.
Huh?
橡果子
Whoa!
我看一下
An acorn.
那里也有
Let me see.
Another one!
捡到了
(GRUNTING)
(GASPS)
Here's one.
别玩了　这样木门打不开
橡果子
Out of the way, Mei. I can't close the door with you there.
有很多橡果子掉到屋里
从上面掉下来的
Acorns.
Dad, acorns are falling from the ceiling.
Falling from the ceiling.
该不会是我们家有松鼠吧
Hmm.
松鼠？
还是　吃橡果子的老鼠呢？
Maybe squirrels live here.
- Squirrels?    - Squirrels?
我喜欢松鼠
I think rats eat acorns. Maybe they're rats.
这要搬到哪儿呢？
- No! Squirrels are better!    - Ew!
放这里，我这就开门
Mister, where do you want your radio?
小月，你去把后门打开
好
Oh, right, the radio. In here's good, I guess.
去了就看得到
- Satsuki, open the back of the house?    - Okay.
快点
- Can you find the back door?    - Of course!
等人家嘛
(GIGGLING)
Come on!
快点
Hey, wait for me!
Well, hurry it up, then.
(ROARING)
进去罗
(SCREAMING)
- Let's go.    - Hmph!
浴室
不见了
- The bath.    - Yep.
这间是浴室
I think they're gone.
爸爸，有怪东西
(GASPS)
松鼠吗？
Hey, you found the bath.
不知道
不像蟑螂也不像老鼠
Dad, something's running around in here.
- More squirrels?    - I don't think so.
只知道是一堆黑色的东西
They're not bugs or mice, either. They were black, and they were all over the place.
Hmm. Let's have a look.
有没有？
那一定是〝灰尘精灵〞
- Ah.    - So?
灰尘精灵
画册里有吗？
It was probably just some soot gremlins.
有啊
今天天气那么好　不可能会有鬼的
What do you mean, “gremlins”? Like the ones in my book?
Well, it could be ghosts,
我们从光的地方　一下子进到暗的地方
but ghosts don't usually like to come out on nice days like this.
眼睛就会发昏　灰尘精灵就会跑出来
Normally, you can't see soot gremlins, but every once in a while,
原来是这样啊
when you go from a bright place to a dark one, you can catch a glimpse of them.
灰尘精灵快点滚出来
So that's it.
你要躲着不出来　我就把你眼睛挖出来！
Come out, come out…
BOTH: Wherever you are!
BOTH: Come out, come out, wherever you are!
(WHOOSHING)
好了，去做事
(LAUGHING)
上二楼的楼梯　到底在哪里呢？
你们两个去把楼梯找出来
Hey, I need your help. It looks like somebody's hidden
然后把二楼的窗户打开
the stairs to the top floor of the house.
好
What?
人家也要
Can you find the stairs and open all the windows up there?
Yeah!
Wait for me!
(GRUNTING)
厕所
Nope.
甚么？
The toilet!
Not here.
甚么？
- Nothing here.    - Nothing here.
- Nope.    - Nope.
甚么？
(LAUGHING)
没有
Ahh!
Nope.
Nope. Hey!
小美，找到了
(CREAKING)
Mei, I found the stairs.
乌漆抹黑的
(GASPS)
灰尘精灵呢？
It's pitch-black.
Maybe it's the soot gremlins.
橡果子
An acorn.
灰尘精灵快点滚出来
Come out, come out, wherever you are!
(RUSTLING)
灰尘精灵
你在不在？
We know you're in here, soot gremlins.
Come on out.
(GASPS)
Huh?
爸爸，真的有怪东西
KUSAKABE: (GRUNTS) Okay, lift.
那真是太棒了
Dad, come here! There's definitely something weird in this house!
爸爸从小就梦想　能够住在鬼屋里面
That's great.
糟了
I've always wanted to live in a haunted house ever since I was a little boy.
BOTH: Oh!
Ahh!
(CRASH)
抓到了！姐姐
I caught one! Satsuki, look!
小美
- Ah!    - Oof!
Hi.
(SHRIEKS)
Mei?
(PANTING)
Oh.
好活泼啊
Whoa. Hey!
这位是一直照顾这个家
(LAUGHING)
住在隔壁的婆婆
What a ball of energy!
婆婆今天是来帮忙的
我叫做小月，这是我妹妹小美
This is our neighbor. She takes care of this house.
婆婆好
She said you can call her “Granny” if you'd like.
好，你们好啊
I'm Satsuki, and that's Mei. Nice to meet you.
这孩子真是聪明伶俐
Well, it's nice to meet you, too.
如果你们不急着搬进来
我还打算请人先收拾一下呢
What nice manners you have.
这样子已经很好了
I'm sorry I didn't have time
现在这时田里农事很忙碌呢
to clean up more before you got here.
KUSAKABE: No, it's fine.
不过我还是偶尔会来打扫
GRANNY: We've been busy in the rice fields,
小美，妳手怎么脏兮兮的？
but I did manage to keep the place well-dusted, as you can see.
怎么弄的？
灰尘精灵跑掉了
Mei, your hands are filthy. What on earth did you do?
妳看妳的脚
I caught a soot gremlin, but he got away.
Ahh! Your feet!
我的脚也脏兮兮的
(GASPS)
哎呀呀！
Mine are black, too!
Ah…
看样子是煤煤虫在作怪
煤煤虫？
你说的煤煤虫是不是会
You've got soot sprites in your house.
〝哇啦哇啦〞的乱跑啊
Soot sprites? The black puff balls? About this big?
是啊
它们专门跑到没人住的旧房子里
They scurry everywhere when you enter a room?
That's right.
然后弄得满屋子的灰尘和煤灰
They live in old, empty houses
我小时候也有看过
and run all over the place, covering everything with dirt.
想不到妳们也看到
I used to be able to see them when I was your age.
婆婆，它们是妖怪吗？
So you've seen them, too. That's very interesting.
其实也没什么好怕的
So they're a kind of ghost, then?
只要对它们笑笑　它们就不会害人
Don't worry, dear. They're nothing to be afraid of.
住上一阵子之后　它们自然就会不见
If they decide you're nice people, they won't harm you,
说不定它们已经在天花板上　讨论该搬去哪里了
and after a while, they'll just go away.
I bet they're up in the rafters right now,
having a talk about whether or not they should move out.
小美，它们很快就会不见了
(JABBERING)
不好玩
可是要是来这么一大堆　该怎么办？
- Hear that, Mei? They're gonna move out.    - I don't want them to leave.
人家才不怕那些
是吗？
What if a huge one came chasing after you?
那以后晚上　姐姐就不陪妳上厕所
So what? I'm not afraid.
Right. Then you can go to the bathroom
来来⋯快来打扫吧
by yourself in the middle of the night.
妳们去河边打点水回来吧
(LAUGHING)
Come on, girls.
河边啊
Let's get to work. Who'd like to fetch some water for the pump?
人家也要去
I'll go get it.
小美，妳在一边等着
I'll go, too!
(LAUGHING)
Mei, wait there, okay?
有没有抓到鱼？
Did you catch a fish?
婆婆，有水了
(GRUNTING)
好好打啊
(SQUEALING)
打到水变凉为止
Granny, the pump's working!
好
Keep pumping!
Don't stop until the water gets cold.
Okay.
(LAUGHING)
你不是刚刚那个吗？　有事吗
我妈妈要给婆婆的
Oh. Hello again. Can I help you?
是什么？
Eh… My… mom said to give this to Granny.
Oh. What is it?
等等，这是什么啊
- Mmm.    - Hmm?
Mmm! Eh…
是勘太吗？
Hey, wait! What is this?
你们家是可怕的大鬼屋
Is that Kanta?
勘太！
Hey, you in there!
- Your house is haunted!    - Kanta!
Mmm.
爸爸以前也这样作弄过女生
(MEI GIGGLES)
(LAUGHING)
男生最讨人厌了
Satsuki, I acted just like that when I was a boy.
不过　婆婆这个糯米团很好吃
那便多吃点啊
I hate boys, but I'm glad he brought this cake you made.
It's great, Granny.
婆婆，谢谢您的糯米团
(KUSAKABE LAUGHS)
Eat all you like.
SATSUKI: Thanks, moving man!
真是太谢谢您了
MEI: Thanks, moving man!
婆婆再见
Thanks for everything, Granny.
- Good-bye, Granny!    - Good-bye, Granny!
(CREAKING)
(POTS RATTLING)
爸爸，我们家　破破烂烂的会否倒下来
要是才刚搬来就倒塌　那可怎么得了
Dad, this house is too old. I think it's gonna fall down.
(LAUGHING)
That would be a problem, since we just moved in here.
(LOUD CRASH)
Huh?
(CLOCK TICKING)
(HOOTING)
(GASPS)
(HOOTING CONTINUES)
我们一起大笑看看
(LAUGHING)
可怕的东西就会跑光
人家才不怕呢！
Everybody, try laughing. Then whatever scares you will go away.
(LAUGHING)
人家才不怕呢！
But, Dad, I'm not scared.
(LAUGHING)
What? I'm not scared.
(ROARING)
(SHOUTING)
(LAUGHING)
一、二、一、二、一、二
很好，加油
BOTH: One, two, one, two, one, two.
用力，加把劲
That's it. Stamp that dirt out, girls. That's it.
好了　衣服都洗好了
Okay. That's all the chores.
- You're done.    - BOTH: Yay!
出发了！
Ready? Hold on!
Who-o-oa!
(GIRLS SHRIEKING)
KUSAKABE: Whoo-ooo!
婆婆
您好！
SATSUKI: Granny!
您可真忙啊
三个一起出门啊？
GIRLS: Hi, Granny! KUSAKABE: Good afternoon!
我们要去医院看妈妈
Hello there, Kusakabes! Where are you headed?
可有好一段路呢
We're going to visit Mom at the hospital!
替我帮妳们妈妈问好
That's good! Say hi!
好的
Tell her I hope she's feeling better.
SATSUKI: We will!
- Mmm.    - Mmm.
走这边！走这边！
Hey, this way. Whoa!
(GIRLS GIGGLING)
大家好
妳好
(DOOR OPENS)
妈妈！
小美妳也来啦
- Good afternoon, ma'am.    - Hello, dear.
爸爸还走错路呢
- Mommy!    - Hi, Mei. It's so good to see you.
真的吗
妳也来啦
Daddy kept getting lost the whole way here, Mom.
今天田里休息一天
是啊
Oh, he did? No school?
爸爸正在跟医生说话
No, it's a rice-planting day.
妈妈很高兴你们都来了
Oh, is that so?
Hey, Mom, Dad's talking to the doctor.
新家怎么样啦
都整理好了没？
I am so happy to see you girls.
So how do you like it in the country? Have you settled in?
甚么？我们家是鬼屋啊
- Yeah.    - Hmm?
妈妈喜欢住鬼屋吗？
Mei's scared…
当然啰
- A haunted house?    - Mmm-hmm.
妈妈真想快点出院　看看鬼长什么样子
Mommy, do you like haunted houses?
小美太好了
我好担心啊
Of course. I'll have to get better soon so I can meet some ghosts.
因为我好怕　妈妈会不喜欢那里
- See that, Mei?    - Mmm-hmm.
那妳们两个呢？
喜欢
Mei was worried that you wouldn't come home if the house was haunted.
妈妈我不怕鬼
- Do you two like it?    - Yeah!
小美的头发都是妳梳的？
I'm not scared at all.
(LAUGHS)
梳得真好
Oh, what cute hair. Did you do this, Satsuki?
要好好谢姐姐啊！小美
可是姐姐动不动就生气
- Mmm-hmm.    - It's very nice, huh, Mei?
还不都是因为妳不乖
- What a lucky girl you are.    - Yeah, but she yells at me a lot.
小月，过来让妈妈看看
你的头发会不会太短了
- That's because you never sit still.    - Let's see your hair, Satsuki.
我喜欢这个样子
人家也要！人家也要！
You sure it isn't a little too short?
排队！
No, I like it this way, Mom.
头发还是一样经常打结
- Brush my hair! Brush mine!    - Wait your turn, Mei.
就跟妈妈小时候一样
那我长大以后
Your hair will never cooperate.
头发会不会　变得跟妈妈的一样呢？
It's exactly like my hair when I was your age.
应该会吧
Do you think it will start cooperating soon?
因为妳跟妈妈最像了
I want it to look like yours.
(CHUCKLES)
I think it will.
You and I are a lot alike, Satsuki.
(INAUDIBLE)
妈妈好像好了很多
是啊
医生也说　再过不久就可以出院了
- Mom looked great, didn't she, Dad?    - Yeah, she did,
再过不久，明天吗？
her doctor said she should be able to come home real soon.
妳什么都是明天
明天可能有点难
- So she'll be home tomorrow?    - There she goes again with tomorrow.
可是人家好想要跟妈妈一起睡
Well, I think tomorrow might be a bit soon.
妳不是说妳已经长大　要自己一个人睡的吗？
Mom said she was gonna sleep in my bed with me.
跟妈妈睡没关系
I thought you weren't scared to sleep alone.
Can't you sleep by yourself?
She's the one who's scared, not me.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
爸爸
天亮了
Hey, Dad! Look, it's morning!
起床！
(GROANING)
- Umph!    - Hey, wake up!
对不起，爸爸又睡过头
(GROANING)
今天开始要带便当
糟糕，爸爸忘记了
- Sorry. I overslept again.    - I have to take lunch to school today.
没关系，我也帮你们做好了
Oh, no. I forgot all about that.
烧焦了
马上来
That's okay. I'm making lunch for everyone.
这是小美的
- Hey, it's burning!    - I'm coming. Just a minute.
我的
小美，坐下来好好吃饭
I'm making this one for you, Mei.
来
I get one?
便当自己包好
Mei, sit down and eat.
There you go. Wrap it up so it stays fresh. Okay?
小月
(SIGHS)
糟了，来啊
- Satsuki!    - That's Michiko.
这么快就交到朋友啦？
Hi!
叫得很真亲密呢
她叫小满
So, you made a friend already, did you?
我吃饱了
- Satsuki, time for school!    - She's walking to school with me.
(SLURPING)
我去上学了
I gotta go.
路上小心啊
(DISHES CLATTERING)
See you later!
早
BOTH: Have a nice day!
早，赶快走吧　好
Hi, Michiko.
- Hi. Ready for school?    - Yep.
(CHILDREN TALKING)
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
爸爸！
你看我像不像姐姐
(YAWNING)
妳拿着便当要上哪儿去？
Hey, Dad.
就在附近走走
Do I look like a big girl?
You do. Are you going somewhere?
I'm just off to run some errands.
爸爸，可以吃便当了吗？
一早就想吃呀？
Dad, is it lunchtime yet?
What? We just ate breakfast.
爸爸你开花店了
Dad, you be the flower shop. Okay?
小蝌蚪！
Hey, tadpoles.
破了一个大洞
What a stupid bucket.
Huh?
发现了
Acorn.
Ha!
(GIGGLES)
(MEI GRUNTING)
(SNORING RESUMES)
(MOANING)
你是谁？
(CHUCKLING)
灰尘精灵吗？
Who are you? A great big soot gremlin?
(GRUMBLING)
(ROARING)
(LAUGHING)
To-to-ro!
龙猫！你叫做龙猫呀？
(INHALES)
Totoro?
Is that what your name is? Totoro?
你一定就叫做大龙猫
(GRUMBLING) Totoro.
大龙猫
Yep, that's your name, all right.
Mmm. Totoro.
(MOANING)
待会见
(PLOP)
我回来了
- Bye.    - See you later!
妳回来啦
都已经这时间啦
- Bye.    - See you later!
小美呢？待会我要去小满家
- I'm home!    - Hi there.
爸爸还没吃便当呢
- Wow. Is it that late already?    - Where's Mei?
小美没有在院子里玩吗？
- Did she like her lunch box?    - We haven't eaten.
小美
She's running around with that lunch box.
Mei!
小美
Mei?
爸爸！　小美的帽子掉在这里
(GASPS)
Hey, Dad! Come here!
I found Mei's hat!
小美！小美！
(GASPS)
Mei! Mei!
(MOANING)
小美！够了，快起来
Hmm? Hmm.
妳干什么睡在这里！
- Hey, Mei, wake up!    - Huh?
大龙猫？
What do you think you're doing, sleeping out here?
怪了
Totoro?
你做梦啦
Where's Totoro?
大龙猫刚才还在的
大龙猫？
Maybe you were dreaming.
你是说画册上那个大妖怪吗？
- No, I saw Totoro.    - Totoro?
它的名字叫做大龙猫啊
You mean a troll, like the one in your storybook?
它的毛好多啊
嘴巴是这样子的
Mmm-hmm. But he called himself Totoro.
有这么小的
He was furry, with a great big mouth.
还有这么大的
还有一只这么大的在睡觉
There was a little one, and a bigger one,
and a huge one that kept falling asleep.
找到了
(SIGHS)
真是个好地方
(TWIGS SNAPPING)
There you are.
简直像是个秘密基地一样
(PANTING)
爸爸
小美说　她看到一只大龙猫
Wow. This would make a great secret hiding place.
大龙猫？
这边！
Dad, Mei said that she saw a Totoro here.
- A Totoro?    - Mmm-hmm.
This way!
妳们两个等等我
(LAUGHING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Hey, wait up!
是这里吗？
Huh?
它刚才　睡在一棵很大的树里面
- Here?    - Mmm-mmm.
可是这里只有一条路啊
Last time the tunnel led to Totoro's tree.
小美，你快回来啊
I didn't see another path to take.
小美，回来啊
Hey, where are you going?
SATSUKI: Mei, come back!
真的有啦
刚才真的有大龙猫
(LAUGHING)
我没有骗你们
Quit laughing! I really did see Totoro!
I'm not lying.
Mmm.
小美啊
人家没有骗你们
Mei?
其实爸爸跟姐姐
It's not a lie, Dad.
也没有认为妳在骗人啊
Hmm. Don't worry, Mei.
小美刚才一定是　遇到了森林的主人
Satsuki and I believe you, and I bet you I know what happened.
这就表示小美运气很好
You must have met one of the spirits of the forest.
不过这种机会并不常有
That means you're a very lucky girl.
来，我们去跟它打个招呼吧
But you can't always see the spirits.
打招呼？
You can only see them when they want you to.
现在向大树出发了
Let's give the forest spirits a proper greeting.
- A greeting?    - Of course. Come on. Let's go.
小美好像变重了
(GASPS)
爸爸，你看那樟树
Oh, Mei, you're getting heavy.
好大啊
Dad, there's that big camphor tree.
It's incredible.
就是它！
是这棵吗？
That's it!
爸爸，快来啊
SATSUKI: That's Totoro's tree? MEI: Yeah!
Come on, Dad! Can't you go any faster?
那个洞不见了
Whoa.
真的是这里吗？
小美她说洞不见了
Totoro's hole is gone.
所以我说啦
- Are you sure it was here?    - Mmm-hmm.
那不是想看　随时就能看到的
还会再看得到吗？
Dad, she says the hole disappeared.
我也好想看啊
Then right now, the forest spirits don't want to be seen.
那得碰运气
But, Dad, I want to see them, too.
这棵树真大啊
Maybe you will, if you're lucky.
一定是从很久很久以前
Mmm. Magnificent tree.
就已经长在这里的
It's been around since long ago,
很久很久以前
back in the time when trees and people used to be friends.
树木跟我们人的感情很好
爸爸就是因为看到这棵树
才会这么喜欢现在这个家的
而且知道　妈妈一定也会喜欢这里
When I saw this tree, I knew this would be a good place for our family to live.
来，我们谢谢它再回家
该吃饭了
And I think it will make your mother feel right at home.
对了　我跟小满约好要到她家去
So, let's give this tree a nice greeting and go eat our lunch.
人家也要去
立正站好！
Then I want to write a letter to Mom and tell her all about this.
多谢您照顾我们家小美
- I will, too!    - Attention!
从今以后还盼您多多关照
请您多多关照
Thank you for watching over Mei and making us feel so welcome here.
我们比赛看谁先到家
ALL: Please continue to look after us.
爸爸偷跑
等人家嘛
- Last one home's a rotten egg!    - Hey, no fair!
小美，快点
MEI: Wait!
等人家嘛
- Uh!    - SATSUKI: Hurry it up!
妈妈，今天出了一件大新闻
Wait for me!
因为小美说她看到了　一只很大的龙猫精灵
SATSUKI: Dear Mom: We had an exciting day today.
Mei met a big forest spirit called Totoro.
我好希望我也能够见它一面
I hope I'll be able to see him someday, too.
(INAUDIBLE)
勘太
再不快点就要迟到了　嗯
WOMAN: Kanta, hurry up, or you'll be late for school.
Yeah.
(CHILDREN LAUGHING)
小美
Oh.
老师
什么事？小月
Mei?
我妹妹⋯
Miss Hara!
Yes, Satsuki?
你们看，你们看，她妹妹
Uh, my sister's here.
CHILDREN: Her sister?
婆婆、小美？
(CLAMORING)
对不起
她一直吵着　要到姐姐那边去所以⋯
- Granny, what's wrong?    - I don't know.
可是
小美
She said she wouldn't stop crying unless I brought her to you.
今天是爸爸　要到大学去教课的日子
我们不是说好了
She said that? Mei, be reasonable.
你要在婆婆家　乖乖等姊姊放学的吗？
You know you had to stay with Granny.
姊姊还要再上两个小时的课
I have school and Dad's teaching at the university.
婆婆的田里又那么忙
I only have two more hours of school to go.
小美在婆婆的家里一直都很乖的
Can't you just stay with Granny until then?
She's been so good up till now. Weren't you, Mei?
婆婆，那我去跟老师说说看
(SIGHS)
Well, I'll talk to my teacher and see what we can do.
现在小月因为妈妈住院
(LAUGHING)
所以妹妹暂时没人照顾
同学们要好好跟她相处啊
Satsuki's mom is in the hospital,
好、好
so her sister Mei is going to stay with us today, okay, class?
这是什么啊
- Let's make her feel welcome.    - ALL: Yes, ma'am.
大龙猫呀
不要吵
- What are you drawing, Mei?    - It's a big Totoro.
Shh. Mei, try to keep quiet, will you?
Mmm-hmm.
(SIGHS)
再见再见，明天见了
(BELL RINGING)
再见
我今天不能去社团了
CHILDREN: Bye, Mei!
我去跟老师说
MICHIKO: Come again soon!
再见了
拜拜，再见
I have to skip our club meeting, Michiko.
小美，快点，要下雨了
I'll let everyone know. Bye!
Hurry up, Mei. It's gonna rain.
Okay.
下雨了
(SPLAT)
(GASPS)
人家都没有哭，棒不棒？　嗯
Come on.
可是真伤脑筋
I didn't even cry. That's good, huh?
Hmm.
土地公爷爷　请您让我们躲一下雨
Yeah, but we're not home yet.
We'd like to share your roof for a while, sir, if you don't mind.
- Mmm.    - Huh?
可是⋯
- Don't you…    - Mmm. Mmm!
Mmm!
Hey!
姊姊，有伞子真棒啊
可是伞子顶破了一个大洞
- That was lucky, wasn't it?    - Mmm-hmm.
- MEI: This umbrella has holes.    - Hmm.
爸爸今天好像没带伞
(EATING)
人家也要去接爸爸
(CLOCK CHIMING)
Dad left his umbrella here.
不就是忘记了
- I'd better take it to him.    - I wanna go, too.
明明都已经下雨了
竟然还会傻得忘了带伞　你骗鬼啊！
What? I left it.
好痛啊
(SIGHS)
我看啊　你八成是把伞子弄坏了
What kind of fool forgets his umbrella at school when it's raining?
才不是呢
- Hey!    - I bet you were swinging it around
and you broke it.
No, I didn't.
(GASPS)
有人在家吗？
Ahh.
小月？还有小美
Hello! Is anyone home?
妈
今天真的是麻烦你们了
Oh, Satsuki and Mei. Come in. Granny!
不用客气
对了　这是勘太今天借我们的伞
Thanks for watching Mei today.
Sorry we couldn't keep her happy.
这孩子⋯
Oh. I wanted to give back this umbrella that Kanta lent us.
这么破的伞子真不好意思
这把伞帮了我们好大的忙
What? He lent you this? Oh, my. Look how beat up it is.
不过却害勘太都淋湿了
麻烦伯母谢谢勘太
Mei was walking home from school with me.
不必客气
So, it was really nice of him to help us out. Tell him thank you.
反正他老是弄得全身都是泥
淋淋雨反而干净些
- He must have been drenched.    - That's okay.
你们要去接爸爸啊
Kanta is such a dirty kid. He can always use a good drenching.
真是孝顺啊
小美，拜拜
Are you off to meet your dad at the bus stop?
拜拜
- SATSUKI: Yes, he forgot his umbrella.    - Such good kids.
- Bye, girls.    - SATSUKI: Bye!
刚才是谁来了呀
(GIGGLING)
才懒得理呢
(IMITATES AIRPLANE)
刚好赶上
- Who was at the door, Kanta?    - Beats me.
(GASPS) There's the bus, Mei!
你们要坐车吗？
开车
Are you getting on?
Drive on.
爸爸没有搭这班车
一定是搭下一班啦
小美，妳到婆婆家等好不好？
Satsuki, Dad wasn't on the bus.
He'll be on the next one for sure.
Do you want to go back to Granny's and wait there?
怎么啦？
What's the matter?
小美
(SIGHS)
妳困啦
早跟妳说过的嘛
What is it, Mei? Are you sleepy?
要不要先到婆婆家去睡一下？
爸爸就快到了　撑着点啊
I knew this would happen. Don't you want to wait at Granny's?
Mmm-mmm.
It's okay, Mei. He'll be here soon.
巴士怎么这么慢
(SIGHS)
That bus sure is late, huh?
来
大龙猫？
等我一下
(GRUMBLING)
这个借你
Oh, wait a minute.
快点啊　小美快要掉下来了啦
Here. Try this.
Hurry. Mei's slipping.
要这样子用
(GRUNTS)
Hold it over your head. Like this.
(THUD)
(SHRIEKS)
(DOUSING)
(ROARING)
巴士来了！
(GASPS)
Oh.
Here comes the bus.
BOTH: Huh?
(WIND WHISTLING)
(YOWLING)
大龙猫　把爸爸的伞给带走了
Well, Mei, so much for bringing Dad his umbrella.
对不起，对不起
开车
爸爸没搭上电车
- Hi. Sorry I'm late.    - WOMAN: Drive on.
所以就没赶上平常那班巴士
害你们担心啦
My train was delayed, so I had to wait for the next bus.
出现了，爸爸　真的出现了
对呀，还有猫的巴士
Were you worried?
Totoro came back, Dad! I saw him!
那辆巴士好大啊
We saw a cat bus, too!
眼睛像这样子啊
- What?    - It was huge!
吓死人了
With eyes like this.
看到了！　我看到大龙猫了！
- It was great!    - It was great!
(LAUGHING)
好棒啊
I saw Totoro! I saw him!
好吓人啊
I saw him, too!
(GIRLS LAUGHING)
(CROAKING)
(INSECTS CHIRPING)
- Hey, Dad, pick us up.    - Come on, Dad.
(GRUNTING)
妈妈
(ALL LAUGHING)
我现在心还在蹦蹦乱跳呢
今天真是既吓人又惊奇　又开心的一天
SATSUKI: Dear Mom:
而且大龙猫送给我们的礼物　实在是太棒了
We had such a weird, mysterious, spectacular day.
是一个用竹叶包着
My heart is still pounding.
然后外面再用　龙须草绑着的小包包
Totoro gave us a wonderful present.
我跟小美回家以后打开一看
It was wrapped in a bamboo leaf
发现里面都是橡果子
and tied with a ribbon made of grass.
As soon as we got home, we opened it.
It was filled with acorns.
(GASP)
我们想家里院子　变成森林的话一定很棒
Ahh.
所以就把它们洒在院子里
(CHUCKLING)
不过
“We wanted to grow a beautiful forest with the acorns,
它们现在都还没有发芽
所以小美每天都一直在说
so we planted them in your garden out back, but…”
还没发芽，还没发芽
SATSUKI: … they just won't grow. Mei watches them
就好像猴子螃蟹大战　里面那个螃蟹一样啊
all day, every day,
waiting for them to sprout,
it's starting to make her crabby.
Here's a picture of Mei as a crab.
学校很快就要放暑假了
(CHUCKLING)
希望妈妈的病　能够快点好起来好吗？
Summer vacation is almost here,
小月
and I can't wait to play outside with you.
Please get well soon. Love, Satsuki.
(GIRLS LAUGHING)
要关灯了
Get ready, and… up!
等等
(SHRIEKING)
(LAUGHING)
爸爸，明天会不会发芽？
- Lights out, girls.    - MEI: Wait, Dad.
这个问题呀
我看要问大龙猫才会知道
Do you think that they'll sprout tomorrow?
晚安
I don't know.
You should ask the Totoro. He would know.
Good night, girls.
(CRICKETS CHIRPING)
小美
Mei.
(GROANING)
那是我们种橡果子的地方
That's where we planted the acorns.
太棒了！
GIRLS: Yay! We did it! We did it!
GIRLS: Yay!
(BELLOWING)
(HUMMING)
小美，我们都变成风了啊
(GRUMBLING)
Mei, we're the wind!
Mmm…
(GASPS)
大树不见了
(GROANS)
Where'd the tree go?
成功了！
- Ahh!    - Ahh!
好像在作梦
They're growing! We did it!
却又不是梦
We did it!
好像在作梦
(LAUGHING)
却又不是梦
万岁！
好啊！
SATSUKI: I thought it was a dream! MEI: But it wasn't!
BOTH: I thought it was a dream! We did it!
草壁先生在吗？电报
草壁先生在家吗？
Mr. Kusakabe? Telegram!
有您的电报
Mr. Kusakabe?
没人在家啊
A telegram for you.
Huh. No one's home.
婆婆
(TRAMPLING)
我在这儿
MEI: Granny!
长成这个样就能吃了
I'm over here.
This one's ready to eat.
(GRUNTING)
婆婆，那这个呢？
(SNAP)
可以
What about this one, Granny?
Try it.
(GRUNTING)
婆婆你的这块田　好像是一座宝山啊
(SNAP)
来，休息一下喘口气
Wow, Granny. Your garden is just like a market.
已经冰透了
We've picked enough, haven't we? Let's take a rest.
那我要吃了
Mmm. Nice and cold.
Mark, get set, go!
好好吃啊
真的呀
这是因为经常被太阳晒
It's delicious.
对身体非常健康的啊
I'm glad you like it. They're very good for you.
对妈妈的身体也有益吗？
They've soaked up lots of vitamins and sunshine.
当然啦
只要是　吃了婆婆田里种的东西
- Would they help Mom get better?    - Of course they would.
身体就会好啦
这个星期六　我妈妈就会回来了
If your mom eats my vegetables, I bet she'd get well right away.
妈妈要跟我一起睡觉啊
That's great, Granny. Mom's coming home on Saturday.
是吗？　马上就要出院了
She's going to sleep with me in my bed.
不算是真正的出院
Oh, good! She's finally leaving the hospital, is she?
星期一还得回去复诊
还没有那么快好
No. The doctor wants her to get used to the new house a little at a time.
这样吗？
那可要多吃点东西补一补了
- She goes back on Monday.    - Is that so?
我要把我自己摘的　粟米给妈妈吃
We'll feed her lots of my vegetables while she's here.
那她一定会很高兴的
I'll give her the corn that I picked. That will make her better.
- I bet that will do her wonders.    - Yep.
电报
你们不在　所以邮差送去我家
给我们的
Here. The postman left us your telegram.
婆婆　我爸爸不到傍晚不回来
A telegram?
快打开看吧　要是急事耽搁就不好了
What should I do with it, Granny? Dad won't be home till evening.
Better open it. Might be an emergency.
发电处七国山医院
Mmm-hmm.
七国山医院送来的
“Please contact Shichikokuyama.”
那就是从妈妈的医院
难道妈妈发生了什么事
“Please contact Shichikokuyama.”
Shichikokuyama! It's from Mom's hospital!
婆婆，怎么办？
Something must have happened to her.
医院要我们跟他们联络
你别紧张，冷静一点
知不知道爸爸上班的地方？
We have to get to the hospital right away, Granny.
爸爸研究室的电话号码　我是知道
Okay. Calm down. First, we need to get in touch with your father.
可是没有电话可打呀
勘太　你带小月去打电话
I know his phone number at the university, but we don't have a phone.
Kanta, take Satsuki to your uncle's house and let her use the phone.
小美妳留下来陪婆婆
Mmm-hmm.
Mei, you need to stay here with me!
小美妳回去婆婆那里
Mei, go back and stay with Granny!
请你接市外电话
请接东京31局1382号
Hello? I'd like to place a long-distance call, please.
好
It's to my dad at Tokyo 31-13-82.
这个女孩还真是讨人喜欢呢
Right.
喂！是的
Now, that's a nice girl, eh, Kanta?
(RINGS)
请问是考古学教室吗？
Hello?
Yes.
我爸爸⋯　麻烦请草壁先生听电话
Hello? I need to speak to my dad in the archaeology department.
我叫做草壁月
I mean, I need to speak to Mr. Kusakabe.
爸爸，是我，小月
My name is Satsuki Kusakabe.
怎么了？
Hello, Dad? Is that you? It's Satsuki.
医院来电报？我知道了
- Satsuki, what's wrong?    - We got a telegram.
爸爸现在就　打电话到医院去问
You're supposed to call Mom's doctor at the hospital.
是不是妈妈出事了
What? The hospital?
怎么办呀？爸爸
Okay. I'll call them right away.
不会有事的
爸爸给医院打过电话　就马上就回妳电话
Did something happen to her, Dad? Do you think she's okay?
你在那边等一下
Let's not worry.
I'll call the hospital, and then I'll call you right back. Okay?
待会儿就打给妳
- Yeah.    - Just wait by the phone.
婆婆　我还可以在这里待一会吗？
- Mmm-hmm.    - I need to hang up now. Okay?
我爸爸还会打电话来
没关系，慢慢来
Excuse me, is it okay if I wait here? My dad says he's going to call me back.
Of course. Make yourself at home.
姊姊
Satsuki!
(PANTING)
不可以啦
(BLEATING)
这个是要给妈妈的粟米
不可以！
Back off! Don't touch my corn!
这个是要给妈妈的啦
It's for my mommy!
(BLEATING)
Too bad! She needs it to make her better.
小美
爸爸说妈妈的病又有点恶化了
所以这个礼拜妈妈不能回家了
Mei, the doctor said that Mom's not doing well.
我不要！
So she doesn't get to come home this weekend.
你不要也不行啊
妈妈要是勉强出院　反而更严重了那怎么办
No fair!
我不要！
It can't be helped, Mei.
不过是晚几天而已
What if she came home early, and it made her even worse?
It's not fair!
我不要！
那妈妈死掉　也没有关系是不是
Mei, we just have to wait a little longer.
不要！
- No!    - You want her to die, Mei?
妳这个大笨蛋！
我不管妳了！
- Is that what you want?    - No!
You're such a baby! Just grow up!
走吧
(SNIFFLING)
姊姊大坏蛋！
Come on, Mei.
(CRYING)
She's so mean!
衣服该收收了
别这么沮丧
婆婆不是过来帮忙了吗
Come on, girls. Let's put the laundry away.
打起精神
Oh, don't be sad. Granny's here to help.
你爸爸说他今天　要留在医院过夜
妳妈妈不过是感冒而已
Don't worry. Your father is going to stop by the hospital.
下个星期六一定会回来的
The doctors say your mom just has a cold.
之前也是这样
She should be home next Saturday.
医生说只要住数天就会好了
而且那次也是说得了感冒
This is just like last time.
我妈妈要是死了该怎么办
They said Mom just had a little cold, she'd be home in a few days.
小月
我妈妈要是死了那我们⋯
Granny, what will we do if she dies?
Satsuki!
Maybe she's dead already.
妳放心，不要乱想
(CRYING)
妳妈妈哪舍得下　妳们这些可爱的孩子
Now, don't say that, sweetheart.
别哭了别哭了
How could she ever leave such sweet girls like you?
在妳爸爸回来之前
Oh, don't cry.
婆婆都会陪着妳的　好不好呀
Don't cry. It's all right.
I'll stay here until your father comes home. Okay? Okay?
小美呀
Mei!
小美
小美回来了没？
Mei!
没在公车站牌那边吗？
这就奇怪了
- Did she come back?    - No.
她会跑到哪里去了？
- She wasn't at the bus stop?    - No.
我刚刚跟小美吵了一架
Let's think.
因为她⋯
Do you know anywhere else she might have gone?
她会不会　跑去妈妈住的医院了
I yelled at her this morning. She wanted Mom to come home.
七国山医院去了呀
Granny, I bet she went to see Mom at the hospital!
可是就连大人也得　走上三个钟头才会到
You think she'd try to walk to the hospital?
我去看看
Why, that's a three-hour walk even for grown-ups.
勘太　快点去叫你爸爸回来
I'll go look.
小美不见了
Kanta! Hurry! Run on home and get your father!
Mei's disappeared, and we need all the help we can get!
小美真是笨蛋　不知道路又爱乱跑
I shouldn't have yelled at her. This is all my fault.
小美
Mei!
打搅了，伯伯，请问⋯
您有没有看见束辫子的小女孩　从这条路经过
Excuse me, mister! Hello!
她是我妹妹
- Yeah?    - I'm looking for my sister.
这个嘛⋯小女孩啊
没什么印象
Did you happen to see a little girl pass this way?
Let's see. Uh, a little girl?
她会不会没往这边来
Mmm, I don't think so. I would have noticed.
I'll try the other road.
妳确定她是往这边来的？
我也不知道
MAN: Are you sure that this is the way she came?
I don't know.
小美
Mei!
(HEAVY BREATHING)
停车！
(CAR APPROACHING)
搞什么啊！危险啊
Stop! Please, stop!
我在找我妹妹
你们有没有看一个小女孩
妳妹妹？
- Oh! Are you crazy?    - I'm looking for my little sister.
她好像是往七国山医院去了
Have you seen a girl walking this way?
她是一个四岁的小女孩
Is she lost?
良子啊，妳刚才有没有看到
I think she's trying to walk to the hospital. She's only four years old.
我们两个　就是从那个方向来的
不过　好像没有看到那样的小孩
Oh. I didn't see her. Did you?
谢谢你们
No. We just came from the hospital,
她从哪里来的？
and there was no sign of a little girl on the road.
松乡
Okay. Thanks.
松乡！？
会不会搞错了呀
- Wait. Where'd you say you're from?    - From Matsugo.
就是啊
Matsugo! Ho!
A four-year-old couldn't walk this far.
(ENGINE STARTS)
MAN: Good luck. I hope you find her.
小月
勘太
Satsuki!
怎么样？
没看到，那妳呢？
Kanta!
现在我爸爸他们也去找了
- Find her?    - No.
我去往七国山的路上看看
- I guess you didn't, either.    - Mmm-mmm.
妳先回家去
My dad's got a bunch of people looking for her.
我想小美一定是想去医院
I could ride my bike to the hospital for you.
可是却走错路了
一定是
- You should go back home.    - Check all around.
刚才有人在神池　发现一只小孩的凉鞋
I'm sure that Mei got lost on her way to the hospital, okay?
A little while ago, they found a sandal in the pond.
不过还不确定　那就是小美的鞋子
(GASPS)
They don't know for sure it's Mei's sandal!
找到了吗？
(BREATHING HARD)
Did you find her yet?
MAN: We'll check the irrigation ditch.
喃呒阿弥陀佛
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
MAN: On the far end.
池那边泥比较深一点　从那边开始啊
(CHANTING)
递根竹竿给我！
It's much deeper over there. You should try there first!
MAN: Are there more poles?
喃呒阿弥陀佛　婆婆，小月来了
(CHANTING)
(CLAMORING)
婆婆
Huh?
妳看看这个
WOMAN: It's Satsuki.
Here. Is this Mei's?
不是小美的
- It's not hers.    - Oh!
(SIGHS)
太好了
Ohh…
(SIGHS)
我还以　这是小美的
Oh, thank goodness.
婆婆就爱穷紧张
I was positively certain that sandal belonged to Mei.
虚惊一场啊
那孩子到底跑到哪去了？
All right. Granny just got carried away.
再去四处找找
Hey! It's not her sandal!
快点啊，天要黑了
不好意思啊
大家辛苦你们　再回头去找找好了
All right everyone, I know you've spent a lot of time here already,
but we still need your help.
求求你们
把我带去龙猫那里
Please.
我的妹妹走丢了
(PANTING)
不久天就要黑了
Let me in to see Totoro. Mei's lost.
她一定在哪里迷了路
It's getting dark, and she's out there all alone.
Please let me in to see him. It's an emergency.
(THUDDING)
(SCREAMING)
大龙猫？
(THUDDING)
大龙猫
(GASPS)
我妹妹小美走失了
Totoro!
我找了好久都找不到
求求你，帮我找小美好不好
Totoro, Mei's lost. I looked everywhere for her, but I couldn't find her.
她一定已经吓哭了
Please help me. I have to find her.
我现在不知道该怎么办好
I'm sure she's scared half to death by now.
I don't know where else to turn.
(SOBBING)
大家都看不到它
(YOWLING)
No one else can see it, can they?
小美
(LAUGHING)
GRANNY: Mei!
(GASP)
Mei!
树林开出了一条路了
The trees are parting!
小美
(SIGHS)
姊姊
SATSUKI: Mei!
Satsuki!
小美
- Where are you?    - Mei!
姊姊
妳这个傻瓜
- Mei!    - Satsuki!
对不起
妳是不是想要把粟米　送去医院给妈妈？
- Oh! You're okay.    - I'm sorry.
Were you trying to take your corn to Mom at the hospital?
Mmm-hmm.
〝七国山医院〞
(YOWLING)
你要送我们去医院吗？
HOSPITAL
谢谢你
You're going to take us to the hospital?
Thank you!
(LAUGHING)
对不起，只不过是感冒
医院就擅自决定　发电报给家里了
I'm sorry. I don't know why the hospital sent a telegram.
那两个孩子一定都很担心我吧
真是苦了她们了
It's just a cold.
她们知道你平安就会安心的
I hope it didn't upset the girls too much. I've caused them enough grief already.
这些年来我们一家四口
不都这样努力过来的吗？
When they see you're all right, they'll be fine.
享福之前总得吃点苦啊
We'll just wait a little longer for a weekend together.
她们表面好像没事　可是心里一定很难过
Don't worry. We've made it this far.
小月越是懂事　就越教人于心不忍
The girls act so strong, but I think it's been harder than they let on.
是啊
Especially Satsuki.
出院以后我一定要好好疼她们
- She tries to act so adult.    - That's true.
让她们尽情耍耍小脾气
I can't wait until I get better.
When I get home, I'm going to spoil those girls rotten.
(LAUGHING)
妈妈在笑
(INAUDIBLE)
看样子是没事了
Look at Mom. She's laughing.
- Everything must be okay.    - Yeah.
我得赶快把身体养好才行
是啊
I'm going to hurry up and get well!
That's the spirit. Huh?
是谁摆的啊？
怎么啦？
Who left this?
我好像看到小月和小美坐在那棵松树上笑
(GASPS)
What is it?
搞不好是真的也说不定啊
I thought I saw Satsuki and Mei smiling at us from up in that tree.
妳看
〝送给妈妈〞
It sounds crazy, but maybe you did.
- Look at this.    - “For Mommy.”
♪ Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ Who leaves the seeds ♪
♪ For you to find ♪
♪ Follow them and you will see ♪
♪ A treasure there ♪
♪ Then plant the seeds ♪
♪ And help them grow ♪
♪ It may seem like a dream ♪
♪ Things are not what they seem ♪
♪ Now begins a new adventure ♪
谢谢观看
♪ For you ♪
♪ And you'll be with Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ Living in the forest trees ♪
♪ For such a very, very long time ♪
♪ There you'll be with Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ You only see him When you're very young ♪
♪ A magical adventure for you ♪
♪ It's magic for you ♪
♪ Rain tumbles down ♪
♪ The bus is late ♪
♪ Suddenly, a furry white giant ♪
♪ Is by your side ♪
♪ Don't be afraid ♪
♪ Just open wide ♪
♪ Your umbrella for him ♪
♪ Watch him play in the rain ♪
♪ Now begins a new adventure ♪
♪ For you ♪
♪ And you'll be with Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ And on a moonlit night ♪
♪ He plays a magic flute in the sky ♪
♪ There you'll be with Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro ♪
♪ Totoro, Totoro ♪
♪ You only see him When you're very young ♪
♪ A magical adventure for you ♪
♪ It's magic for you ♪